A Guide to the J. Austin Kerr papers FA1282
Rockefeller Archive Center
J. Austin Kerr papers
1925-1976
Rockefeller Archive Center
Kerr, J. Austin (1900-1990)
Rockefeller Foundation
FA1282
4.2 Cubic Feet 5 letter document boxes, 4 legal document boxes, 1 flat file folder, and 1 half legal document box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
The J. Austin Kerr papers document Dr. Kerr's 40-year career with the Rockefeller Foundation where he studied and implemented methods to control and eradicate yellow fever, malaria, and hookworm disease. During his career, Kerr lived in Paraguay, Brazil, Nigeria, Colombia, Egypt, Italy, India, the Philippines, and the U.S. The collection contains memos, personal and professional correspondence, critiques of institutions, drafts of papers, notes, research reports, photographs, gifts presented to Kerr, and Kerr's manuscript collection. The manuscript collection is comprised of 159 documents cataloged by Kerr that include published papers, memos, drafts, personal correspondence, and reflections on his work. The majority of the materials in series 1 are duplicated in series 2. Kerr annotated many of the documents from 1970-1976 during his retirement.
Biographical / Historical
John Austin Kerr was born July 15, 1900, in Chicago, Illinois. He received a B.S. from Northwestern University in 1923, and he received an M.D. from Northwestern Medical School in 1924. From 1923 to 1925, he completed an internship at St. Luke's Hospital in Chicago. From July 1925 to June 1926, he conducted epidemiological field studies of hookworm infestations in Alabama and Florida at the Field Training Station of the International Health Board of the Rockefeller Foundation (IHB/RF) in Andalusia, Alabama. This assignment started his long career with the Rockefeller Foundation. From June to September 1926, he worked at the Malaria Field Station of the IHB/RF at Edenton, North Carolina where he studied malaria and malaria control. Starting in October 1926 until March 1928, Kerr worked with Brazil's Yellow Fever Service learning antilarval techniques in Salvador, Bahia, Brazil. From May 1928 to April 1929, Kerr worked in Paraguay on a hookworm control program. From April to June 1929, Kerr worked in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil during the yellow fever epidemic. Following the death of Dr. Paul Lewis from yellow fever in June 1929, Kerr worked at the Yellow Fever Laboratory in Bahia, Brazil. At this time, he contracted yellow fever himself.
From 1930-1931, he was assigned to the Rockefeller Foundation's Yellow Fever Laboratory in Lagos, Nigeria. In 1932, Kerr married Janet MacLennan. From March to November 1932, he investigated potential yellow fever cases in Colombia. He returned to Brazil from 1933 to 1936 to lead the Bahia Laboratory following the death of Dr. Nelson Davis. From 1936 to 1938, he oversaw construction of a lab in Bogota to investigate yellow fever activity in Colombia. From 1939 to 1943, Kerr was stationed in Brazil again where he worked on yellow fever studies and supervised large scale production of 17D yellow fever vaccines. After a few months at the Virus Laboratory of the California State Health Department, he was appointed to the Rockefeller Foundation Health Commission and as a Consultant to the Secretary of War. From July-November 1945, Kerr was Director of the Gambiae Eradication Service of Egypt. From September 1946 to October 1947, he accepted a Rockefeller Foundation assignment to Sardinia to serve as Superintendent of Ente Regionale per la Lotta Anti-Anofelica in Sardegna (ERLAAS), a temporary government entity created to eradicate Anopheles labranchiae. From 1947 to 1951, Kerr worked at the Virus Laboratories of the Rockefeller Foundation located at the Rockefeller Institute (now University) in New York City. There, he studied the influenza virus and arboviruses and wrote the chapter on Clinical Aspects in Yellow Fever edited by George K. Strode. From 1951-1955, Kerr was the Director of Virus Research Centre in Poona, India. From 1955-1965, he served as Director of the Pan American Health Organization (PAHO) stationed in Washington, D.C. After 40 years with the Rockefeller Foundation, Kerr retired on March 31, 1965 just prior to his mandatory retirement from the Foundation.
In March 1965, he was appointed Regional Malaria Advisor for the Far East Region of the Agency for International Development of the U.S. (AID) stationed in Manila, Philippines. In 1966, he was transferred to Washington and discharged from service after critiquing the agency's malaria eradication methods. In 1967, Kerr spent a year as a consultant to the Malaria Eradication Branch of the Pan American Health Organization. There, he translated malariological studies from Portuguese to English. The studies had been conducted in El Salvador by the Epidemiological Study Team of PAHO. In 1968, he was a Guest Scholar at the National Library of Medicine to assist his friend and colleague Fred Soper (sometimes abbreviated FLS) in editing his book, "Selections from the Papers of Fred L. Soper." Kerr lived in Chevy Chase, Maryland until 1986. He died December 12, 1990 in Ossining, New York.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged "as received" in two series:
1. Personal Papers, 1925-1976
2. Manuscripts, 1927-1974
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The J. Austin Kerr papers arrived in several shipments from 1968-1976. George Harrar, president of the Rockefeller Foundation, first contacted J. Austin Kerr about donating his personal papers to the Rockefeller Foundation in 1967. In May 1968, Kerr donated two memos: 1.) A review of the efficacy of vaccination against yellow fever as applied in 1938 and 1939 in Brazil; and 2.) Further considerations on the results obtained following the use of the "17DD high" substrain of 17D virus as vaccine.
Archivist Mary Boccaccio followed up with Kerr about donating more of his materials in March 1969. In January 1970, he donated two manuscripts 1.) "Sylvan, or jungle, yellow fever in southern Brazil, 1932-1942;" and 2.) "The eradication of Anopheles gambiae from Egypt."
In June 1970, Kerr donated a yellow fever manuscript and 20 miscellaneous memos and reports. These materials comprise the first series in the collection. In correspondence from June 1970, he describes his 100+ papers that make up his manuscripts collection. He was still in the process of cataloging the early material at this time. The manuscript materials arrived in five packages in September and October 1974. Series 2 is composed of this material. In 1976, Kerr donated a leather souvenir portfolio and inscribed parchment presented to him in Cagliari, Sardinia.
This material was originally labelled as Accession 13.
Yellow fever; Malaria; Viruses -- Research; Epidemiology; DDT (Insecticide); Aedes aegypti; Anopheles gambiae; Hookworm disease; Yellow fever -- Vaccination
- Personal Papers, 1925-1976; 1; 1.47 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes, 1 legal document box, and 1 half-legal box
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains memos, drafts, notes, research reports, photographs, and gifts presented to Kerr. Many of the reports and drafts are duplicated in Kerr's manuscript collection in series 2. The items in this series were sent to the Rockefeller Archive Center between 1968 and 1970. Around the time of donation, Kerr added additional notes to many of the papers included either in the margins or in letters accompanying the documents.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged "as received."
  - Organization of Campaigns Against Yellow Fever by J. H. White, International Health Board of the Rockefeller Foundation, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Technic for the Use of White Mice for the Recovery of Yellow Fever Virus, From Suspect Human Cases of Yellow Fever - Draft with Edits, 1935 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Note from Kerr from April 7, 1972: This was a pinoneer project because mice had not previously been used to isolate yellow fever virus. With the collaboration of Dr. L? Whitman, if I can recall correctly.
  - The Concept of Selective Measures in Malaria Eradication by J. Austin Kerr, M.D., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Copy - RFA, VII Congresses, Rio de Janeiro
  - Yellow Fever Research Service - Brazil, Special Report for the Period July 1, 1941 to June 30, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - What to Bring to Brazil by Janet M. Kerr, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ente Regional per la Lotta Anti-Anofelica in Sardinia Papers and Photographs, 1947-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes Dr. Kerr's notes about the documents from 1976 when he donated his materials to the Rockefeller Archive Center.
  - Souvenir Portfolio from Cagliari, Sardinia, 1947 October; Leather portfolio 12" x 8.5" (Box 10, Folder 61)
    Received at ceremony when he left his role as Director of Ente Regionale per la Lotta Ani-Anofelica en Sargegna (ERLAAS)
  - Illuminated Parchment Commending Work in Sardinia, 1947 October (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Includes Italian transcription and English translation.
  - Yellow Fever Conference at the Institute for Medical Research, Kuala Lumpur, 1954 January (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Poona, India, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, Lectures, and Papers by J. Austin Kerr with Commentary from Kerr, 1933-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Laboratory Technics - Brazil, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - A Neutralization Test for Yellow Fever Virus Antibodies Using Three-Day Old Mice Inoculated Subcutaneously - Unpublished Experiment, 1942-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - Letter to Mother Regarding Trip to Northern Nigeria, 1931 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Malaria, Yellow Fever, and Mosquito Research Notes, Reprints, and Correspondence, 1933-1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - J. Austin Kerr and Fred L. Soper, Manila, Philippines, 1965 July-1966 August (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Revista Brasileira de Malariologia e Doenças Tropicais, Vol. XXV, N. 1/4, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    Includes note from Kerr explaining his contributions to the paper - edited the text and prepared the tables
  - Working Papers, Drafts, and Notes, 1942-1965 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Headshots, 1942-1971; 2 photographs (Box 2, Folder 20)
    July 1971, age 71
    1942, Rio de Janeiro
  - Rockefeller Foundation Staff Newsletter - J. A. Kerr Retires, 1965 April (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Manuscript of Yellow Fever by J. Austin Kerr, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Original typescript submitted to Dr. LeRoy Sloan (editor of Tice-Sloan) Practice of Medicine Vol. IV - Infectious Diseases, pp. 1-31, Revision of 1960
  - Reports and Memos, 1956-1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Eradication of Anopheles gambiae from Egypt by J. Austin Kerr, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Sylvan, or Jungle, Yellow Fever in Southern Brazil by J. Austin Kerr (manuscript), 1944 February 1 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - 17D Vaccine Memos - Brazil, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Memos:
    1. A Review of the Efficacy of Vaccination Against Yellow Fever as Applied in 1938 and 1939 in Brazil
    2. Further observations on the results obtained following the use of the "17DD high" substrain of 17D virus as vaccine
- Manuscripts, 1927-1974; 2; 3.21 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes, 4 legal document boxes, and 1 flat file folder
  This series contains 159 documents that Dr. John Austin Kerr referred to as his manuscript collection. The documents are numbered in order by date and primarily comprise his published works, memos, personal and professional correspondence, notes, writings from his wife Janet Kerr, and unpublished drafts. The manuscripts span from 1925-1970. Kerr sent the manuscripts in several shipments to the Rockefeller Archive Center in 1974. He included annotations and cataloging notes from that time. There is an index and table of contents in this series and the titles of individual numbered manuscripts are further described at the folder level.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  The manuscripts were received in five packages in September and October 1974 by the Rockefeller Archive Center.
  This series is arranged "as received" by the Rockefeller Archive Center. Kerr arranged many documents by folder size and that has contributed to the order of the documents in this series. Kerr created the manuscript numbering system in his retirement.
  - Prospect for Malaria Eradication in Thailand in 1965, Number 133, 1959-1967 (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
  - Manuscripts by J. Austin Kerr, Numbers 134-158, 1958-1974 (Box 3, Folder 30, 32, Box 4, Folder 33-34)
    Folder 30:
    134 - Informe Mensal Statistico - Preliminar (Monthly Statistical Report - Preliminary) from the Campanha da Erradicação de Malaria (C.E.M.) to AID/Brazil, Devised and proposed by JAK, but probably never implemented
    135 - Procedure for making the Definitive Quarterly Evaluation of the Status of the Malaria Eradication Operations of the Campanha de Erradicação de Malaria (CEM) of Brazil
    Folder 32:
    136 - Summary of the Aerial Reconnaissance of the Philippines, December 1965
    137 - Trip to Kertessia problem area in Santa Catarina and Parana States, March 1966
    138 - Kerring on Project Coordinator for the Malaria Eradication Program for USAID/Brazil, March 1966
    140 - Comments by J. A. Kerr on Memo From John W. McDowell to Dr. Horace Delien, Dated July 8, 1958
    142 - Epidemiological Evaluation of the Results of Malaria Eradication Operations in the Attack Phase, J. Austin Kerr, July 1, 1966
    Folder 33:
    143 - Instructions for Making Preliminary Investigation of a Malaria Case, July 1965
    144 - End-of-Tour Report, Regional Malaria Advisor, Far East, April 20, 1965-August 15, 1966, August 3, 1966
    145 - The Delimitation of the Malarious Areas of a South East Asian Country, August 4, 1966
    146 - An Exercise in Planning, Programming, and Budgeting a National Malaria Eradication Program, August 11, 1966
    147 - Ecology in Malaria Eradication, CDC Atlanta Lecture
    148 - Trip Report of my Visit to the Area of the HCH Pilot Project in Guerrero State, Mexico, 1967 February
    Folder 34:
    149 - Report of Visit to the Plan Piloto De Ataque Integral (PPAI) of the CNEP, February 1-8, 1967
    150 - The age and sex distribution of diagnosed malaria cases in relation to the age and sex distribution of the blood slides collected - Mexico, 1966-1967
    151 (also labelled 143?) - Age and Sex Distribution in a one-week Sample of Blood Slides from the PRIAL (sp? Plan de Responsabilidad Individual en Areas and Limitadas), 1967 February
    152 - Some Thoughts about the Global Malaria Eradication Campaign, August 27, 1967
    153 - Travel Report on Visit to Malaria Eradication Pilot Projects in Mexico (October 1-13, 1967)
    154 - Evaluation of Case Detection in the PRIAL (sp? Plan de Responsabilidad Individual en Areas and Limitadas) Area (Morelos State, Mexico) in 1966 and 1967, December 1967
    155 - Public Health in Latin America, PSI, March 12, 1968
    156 - The Eradication of Aedes Aegypti, December 14, 1968
    157 - Mosquito-Borne Disease Around the World: Remarks at a Seminar of Mosquito Biology Training Program, Vector Biology Laboratory, University of Notre Dame, April 15, 1970
    158 - Comments by JAK on The Place of Persistent Insecticides in the Control of Anthropod Vectors of Disease, Vector and Biological Control Division of WHO/Geneva, November 27, 1970
  - Topographic Maps to Accompany Ecology in Malaria Eradication, Lecture by J. Austin Kerr at Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, 1966 September 30 (Folder 62)
    Accompanied manuscript number 147 - Ecology in Malaria Eradication, CDC Atlanta Lecture
  - A Plan for Visualizing Case Detection Data in Order to Facilitate Analysis and Improve Reporting, Number 74, 1961 January 11 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Written by JAK, but never formally approved by PASB/ME for general use by national malaria eradication services
  - Manuscripts by J. Austin Kerr, Numbers 70-97, 1947-1966 (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
    Folder 36:
    70 - J. Austin Kerr's corrections to Yellow Fever in the Merck Manual of Diagnosis and Therapy, 1966
    71 - Entomological Studies in Panama, May 22-July 22, 1960
    72 - Some Thoughts About Malaria Eradication, March 1, 1960
    73 - Shannon Trap, July 6, 1960
    75 - Determination of local mean times of sunrise and sunset at any place in the world between latitudes 0 and 30N, 1961
    76 - Outline for the Field Study of Suspect Chloroquine-Resistance in a P. falciparum Infection in Brazil, January 1962
    77 - Malaria - Research Needs and Opportunities in Latin America, Some Background Information, 1962
    78 - PAHO/ME Guide Lines for Entomological Studies, June 28, 1962
    79 - Yellow Fever Studies, 1962?
    80 - Plan Piloto de Larvicidas, or Pilot Project of Larviciding, 1962
    81 - Bio-assay with Anopheles albimanus of DDT and Malathion Residues in Houses in El Salvador, Central America, Read on December 4, 1962 at the Annual Meeting of the Entomological Society of America, Phoenix, Arizona
    82 - Mexico, 1947
    83 - A note about the NET ANNUAL MALARIA REPRODUCTION (NAMR) RATE, March 21, 1963
    84 - Some Thoughts About the Possibility That Mass Drug Administration May Be of Major Importance in the Area of Malaria Eradication in El Salvador, March 29, 1963
    85 - Pruebas de Excito Repelencia, Instructivo para su ejecución utilizando las cajas de excito-repelencia, Modelo OPS, April 1963
    Folder 37:
    86 - A Sophisticated Malaria Eradication Program for Central America, July 2, 1963
    87 - Primer Plan Decenal de Salud de El Salvador - Lucha Antipalúdica, May 31, 1963
    88 - The Recognition and Delineation of Areas of Stable Malaria: An Operational Research Program, June 3, 1963
    89 - On the Diagnosis and Treatment of the Malaria Eradication Problem Areas in El Salvador, Central America, August 3, 1963
    90 - Fifth Annual Course in Military Entomology, Malaria Eradication Problems in Tropical America, August 8, 1963
    91 - Preliminary Note on the Epidemiological Studies Made in El Salvador to Determine the Causes of the Failure of Residual Spraying to Interrupt the Transmission of Malaria, 1963
    92 - Analysis of Malaria Parasite Densities, Falla, El Salvador, July 1961-September 1962, September 1963
    93 - Procedure for Making the Epidemiological Evaluation of the Results of the Larviciding Demonstration in El Salvador, C. A., October 28, 1963
    94 - Results of Recent Malariological Field Research in El Salvador, Central America, November 8, 1963
    95 - Procedure for Making an Epidemiological Evaluation of any specific field operation intended to interrupt the transmission of malaria in a problem area, November 1963
    96 - Malaria Eradication Studies in El Salvador I. Evaluation of Larviciding Procedures in Interruption of Transmission, December 4, 1963
    97 - Malaria Eradication Studies in El Salvador II. Evaluation of the Excito-Repellency of Selected Insecticides Alone and Applied Over DDT Residues
  - Proposed Trial in Mexico of the new Pan American Health Organization (PAHO)/Malaria Eradication (ME) Form 22: Resumen de Operaciones de Erradicacion en Mexico - Contained in Memo ME 2021-64 from JAK to Dr. da Silva, Chief of the Malaria Eradication Branch of PAHO, Number 109, 1964 November (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Manuscripts by J. Austin Kerr, Number 98-108, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    98 - Malaria Eradication Studies in El Salvador, III. Bio-Assay Studies of the Duration of Activity of Six Insecticides After Application to Mud Walls
    99 - Notes on a meeting of AID personnel and the Assessment Team with Pacific Health Organization staff personnel to discuss the report of the: Central America Malaria Eradication Assessment Team, May 7, 1964
    100 - Malaria case detection ratio charts
    101 - Conference on Military Entomologists, Excito-Repellency of Anopheles Mosquitoes - A Phenomenon of Newly-Recognized Importance in Malaria Control and Eradication
    102 - Lo Que Es Nuevo En La Erradicación de la Malaria, Trabajo presentado en el XV Congreso de Medicina - Guatemala City, 1964 November
    103 - Field Trial of an Integrated Attack on Malaria in the Costa Chica of Guerrerp and Oaxaca, Mexico, July 28, 1964
    104 - Memo to Dr. Wilbur Downs about trip to Mexico, December 7-14, January 2, 1964
    105 - Aide Memoire, Objective of the Epidemiological Studies in Mexico, January 1964
    106 - CNEP program of Estudios Especiales, January 22, 1964
    107 - On the Use of Ratio Paper for Charting Malaria Case Detection Data, October 28, 1964
    108 - Annual Meeting at CNEP Headquarters in Mexico City, November 19-21, 1964
  - Sylvan, or Jungle, Yellow Fever in Southern Brazil - 1932-1942 by J. Austin Kerr (Incomplete Copy, Original Typescript sent to Archives), Number 40, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Yellow Fever Research Service Ministry of Education and Health Brazil, Annual Report for 1942 - Draft, Number 41, 1942-1974 (Box 5, Folder 41, Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Manuscripts by J. Austin Kerr, Numbers 1-39, 1927-1970 (Box 6, Folder 43-45)
    Folder 43:
    1 - Malaria Survey of Byne's Plantation, Lee County, Georgia, September 1925
    2 - On the epidemiology of aegypti-transmitted yellow fever in rural Northeast Brazil, Parahyba, September 26, 1927
    3 - Report of the Comissão de Febre Amarella, 1970
    4 - Report of Inspection of aedes aegypti control work in Natal, March 3-13, 1928
    5 - Notes on my Trip to the Paraguayan Chaco, September 17-27, 1928
    6 - Comunicado Para la Prensa de la Campafia Sanitaria, November 1928
    7 - Campana Sanitaria - Departamento Nacional De Higiene Y Asistencia Publica Resumen De Los Informes Del Quinquenio, 1924-1928, 1929
    8 - Inspection of Macahe, Yellow Fever, May 12th to 14th, 1929
    9 - Memorandum Regarding the Occurrence of Yellow Fever in Sao Salvador, Bahia, 1901 to 1909, August 1929
    10 - History of illness of J. Austin Kerr (yellow fever), Resident at Pensao Edith, Working at Yellow Fever Lab, Montserrat, Bahia, Brazil, August-September 1929
    11 - Yellow Fever in North Brasil, 1922-1929, 1930
    12 - Preservation of Yellow Fever Virus in Monkey Blood Dried in the Frozen State, undated
    13 - Annual Report 1930, West African Yellow Fever Commission (Portion Written by J. Austin Kerr)
    14 - Letter to J. Austin Kerr's mother about trip to Northern Nigeria, Lagos, February 2, 1931
    15 - Sketches from My Andian Notebook by J. Austin Kerr, 1932
    Folder 44:
    16 - Recent Research in Yellow Fever (Notes for lecture at U. of C. Dept. Bacteriology (N. P. Hudson), January 21, 1932
    17 - The Epidemiological Importance of the Experimental Vectors of Yellow Fever in West Africa, Henry Beeuwkes and J. Austin Kerr, From the Laboratory of the West African, Yellow Fever Commission of the Rockefeller Foundation at Lagos, Nigeria, 1933
    18 - Memorandum to Doctor Soper, Recommendations regarding larvicidal oil, May 23, 1933
    19 - Memorandum to Dr. Sawyer on the Possibility of Substituting Groups of Six Mice by Groups of Five Mice in the Routine Testing of SERA by the Protection Test, Rio de Janeiro, April 15, 1935
    20 - Proposed Field Investigation looking toward the discovery of an animal reservoir of yellow fever virus, Rio, August 12, 1935
    21 - Draft - Instructions for Numbering and Documenting Native Monkeys, Rio, November 16, 1935
    22 - PanAmerican Medical Society Meeting, Viscerotomy Discussion by J. A. Kerr, Rio, Nov (?) 1935
    23 - Criação de Camundongos Laboratório da Bahia, January 1936
    24 - Memorandum Regarding Mass Vaccination Against Jungle Yellow Fever, Londrina, Parana, March 7, 1936
    25 - Examination by JAk at Johns Hopkins of sections from 15 human livers, originally diagnoses as having Midzonal Necrosis, seeking for lesions that could be confused with those of yellow fever, May 1936